I want us to jump straight into it. I
know it's it's uh
reminds me of the Ukraine war, the guys
of war. Sometimes these things are
unfathomable until they happen and then
they just become the norm, which is what
concerns me. But uh a whole lot of
discussion.
Absolutely correct.
I I want to start with a a great summary
you did on your channel, I think
yesterday. It's a 5-minute video for
memory. And you kind of gave an overview
of how this all started
and where we're at today. I'd love you
to give this overview now, but also
update us on the developments in the
last 24 hours, like every day counts.
Um just for the audience on your take on
it
um what led to it where we're at now and
what you expect to happen next and then
we can start digging into all the
points.
Oh, sure. This is an immensely
complicated uh situation. It needn't be,
but it is. And if if it's okay with you,
I want to start with the most important
point up front. One of the most valuable
lessons that I learned in years at the
CIA, especially in years at the CIA
working on the Middle East, is that if
you really want to understand US policy,
it's that you must watch American naval
movements.
We can threaten, our politicians can be
belligerent and give speeches on Capitol
Hill, but if you really want to see what
the American government is planning to
do, watch the movement of naval assets.
Uh in
in 2000 um I'm sorry, forgive me. In
1990, when Iraq invaded Kuwait, uh we
were very serious about pushing Iraq out
of the country. But until then, we had
never put an aircraft carrier in the
Persian Gulf. And the reason why that
had never happened is that the
conventional wisdom was that the Persian
Gulf was too shallow
and there wasn't enough room for an
aircraft carrier to move around. It
takes an an extraordinary amount of
space to just turn the thing around.
Well,
by February of 1991, we had six aircraft
carrier battle groups in the Persian
Gulf.
I said a couple of weeks ago on my own
podcast that
I didn't think this was going to amount
to much, at least not in the near term,
because we weren't moving our naval
assets. Well, we're moving our naval
assets now. Uh just yesterday, President
Trump ordered two more aircraft carrier
battle groups led by the USS Nimitz
uh into the region.
There were already
two carrier battle groups in the region,
and there was a third one in the Indian
Ocean.
Now I'm worried.
I'm worried because it's unclear exactly
what US policy is. So, with that said,
and that aside, what I said in this
short video was that
we don't have to
love the Iranians. We don't even have to
like the Iranians, but we ought to be
able to sit down and negotiate a deal
with the Iranians. Now, I am absolutely
1,000% not a fan of Barack Obama.
It was Barack Obama who put me in prison
after I blew the whistle on the CIA's
torture program.
But,
the JCPOA, also known as the the Iran
nuclear deal,
actually was working. And the the
structure
by which it was uh negotiated was the
same exact structure
with which we negotiated Iraqi
inspections uh during the 2002 to let's
say 2005 period, where um international
inspectors led by the IAEA, the
International Atomic Energy Agency,
uh would go to the the sites. They would
inspect the sites at random,
unannounced. They would seal the sites
with lead seals, and they installed very
sophisticated cameras that that analysts
watched in Geneva. I'm sorry, in in
Vienna, 24 hours a day, 7 days a week to
make sure that that these uh areas were
not being breached or violated. That's
the same deal that was included in the
JCPOA.
What put the United States in a tough
spot with the JCPOA is that
once it was negotiated and approved, it
opened up trade, granted limited trade,
between Iran and
the United States a little bit, but more
importantly, the UK, France, Germany,
and Japan.
We also have a law in this country, and
this is the fly in the ointment, that if
another country trades with Iran,
that we are compelled to put sanctions
on that country.
So, everybody jumps into the JCPOA.
Donald Trump is elected president. He
pulls out of the JCPOA. That immediately
triggers this other American law saying
that we now have to sanction the
British, the French, the Germans, and
the Japanese. Well, we're not going to
do that. They're our most important
trading partners.
And so, it turns out that pulling out of
the JCPOA really didn't get us anything
that we didn't have, and in fact, is
forcing the Treasury Department to
violate US law by not imposing sanctions
on our allies.
So, you have all of that stacked on the
one side.
And then, topping it
is ongoing Iranian support for the
former regime in Syria, for Hezbollah,
and more immediately for Hamas.
It's one thing if you want to support
those countries and entities
uh uh
diplomatically. Nobody cares. You're
going to stand up at the United Nations,
give a speech.
Everybody's going to smile and nod and
listen to their translations and then
you go about your business. But
providing them with with rockets and
grenades and mines and and
digging equipment and secure
communications, that's an entirely
different issue.
Um that's where the United States is
budding heads with Iran. It's and it's
as though it's as though the two sides
just simply can't understand
the other's position.
I get that the Iranians want to support
Palestinian human rights. Lots of people
want to support Palestinian human
rights. That doesn't mean lots of people
want to send weapons to Hamas.
Um
conversely
the United States just and and I I say
this with 20 years of foreign policy and
intelligence policy experience. The
United States just doesn't understand
why the Iranians can't move on from the
American overthrow of the Iranian
government in 1953 and the US response
to the Iranian revolution 1979.
It's just like we we need to your Katie
each other.
And that's that's fine if it doesn't
mean that you that you periodically end
up clashing militarily. And now we're in
a position where
we're going to have to make a decision
here in the United States as to whether
or not we want to rush into support the
Israelis
or not. And let me add one more thing
Mario if I'm if I may.
Starting with Ronald Reagan
literally every single time
that Benjamin Netanyahu came to the
United States to see an American
president
he would ask us to bomb Iran.
Every single time.
And every president from Ronald Reagan
onward said no, we're not going to bomb
Iran for you.
It doesn't make any sense for American
policy, right? There there is no such
thing as permanent friends, the old the
old saying goes.
Only permanent interests.
And it was not in US interest to bomb
Iran.
Well, now we've kind of been put into a
corner where Netanyahu went and did it
unilaterally.
He received now the Iranian response.
And his
his response is to call out the United
States and say Israel's threatened. The
threat is existential. You have to help
me.
So, we're kind of in a tough position
right now.
That was a a great overview.
And I've got a a list of questions on
all the points you've made. Can you
expand your overview to also include the
situation on the ground right now? The
initial strikes by Israel, what your
thoughts are on those. Iran's response.
Um or lack thereof. And
you can also include Hezbollah and the
Houthis, especially Hezbollah's
distancing.
Oh, sure.
Um
the bottom line is there's no way the
the Israelis can lose this fight.
They're they're so far superior to the
Iranians in every respect that they just
can't lose this fight.
With that said,
the number of surface-to-air missiles
that the Israelis possess is finite. The
the Iron Dome can't last forever. It can
last for about a week and a half.
And we're already at day six.
After that, they're going to need uh US
assistance. Now, there have been rumors
that it's been Americans manning missile
batteries and that the Iron Dome
responses that we're seeing in the sky
are not exclusively Israeli uh rockets.
They include American rockets. There are
Patriot missile batteries there and
there are Americans manning those
batteries. So,
it's probably
the Israelis probably have a little bit
more than than 10 days worth of worth of
rockets.
You could see, almost like flipping a
switch, when the Israelis realized, "Oh,
crap, this is going to last a little bit
longer than we thought." in that
they
they began targeting civilian uh
installations in Iran. The first few
days, they were hitting IRGC
headquarters, they were hitting the Quds
Force headquarters, they hit the the uh
nuclear sites, exactly the targets we
expected them to hit.
But now they're hitting
um
Press TV, the Iranian national
broadcaster, they're hitting the sewer
system and the water treatment facility
for Tehran. They're they're hitting
sites that
while technically illegal under um under
international law,
would force the Iranians
to sue for peace or to ask for
intervention,
some sort of a middleman.
Um
Again, with that said,
Israel's a nuclear power. Iran is not a
nuclear power. The Israelis, of course,
would not use a nuclear weapon unless
unless they were threatened with the
destruction of Israel, which is not
happening. It's not a threat. It won't
be a threat.
Uh
but they they can't keep up this fight
forever.
On the last point you made regarding
Iran pivoting to hitting Press TV, the
sewer system, the water treatment
facility,
is that because of a change of strategy?
Because initially Iran's Israel said,
"It's going to be a 2-week war. Prepare
for a 2-week war." Then, well, I think
they quickly they shifted it to it's
going to be many weeks.
Um I'm curious to see is that just their
audacity based on their success and
maybe the the objective changed from
destroying their nuclear capabilities or
forcing them to the negotiation table to
pivoting to a a regime change, which is
a lot more significant.
You know, isn't that
Don't you just want to take politicians
and and strangle them sometimes? I hate
when I hear those words regime change. I
hate it. I still remember in 2001,
20 of my CIA colleagues standing around
a TV watching George W. Bush give a give
a press conference and for the first
time he used the term regime change and
we all groaned out loud like, "Oh, no."
Instead of a 6-month war, this is going
to be 20 years. And it was 20 years. The
Israelis risk doing the same thing, just
getting themselves
overly committed where they just can't
they can't win a long drawn out war.
Look at it this way, too.
Israel has about 10 million people. Iran
has about 90 million people.
And unless you have such incredible air
superiority that you can just bomb them
back into the Stone Age, which they
don't,
you can't win a long-term war. The
longer this drags out, the worse it is
for Israel.
Just over the last couple of days,
Mario, the Israelis have said
well, two things. One, the Israelis and
the IAEA said
that um
it turns out that there has been no uh
leak of radioactivity at the sites that
Israel bombed on the first day. They
thought there was a leak, turns out
there's not a leak. Secondly,
the Israelis are asking the United
States for bunker buster bombs. Bunker
busters can um can penetrate up to 200
ft deep. What is that? About uh 65 m
deep. The Israelis don't have bunker
busters, the Americans do. And so
they're asking us to either give them
the bunker busters or bomb Iran
ourselves.
And we can't because we risk triggering
the Russians and the Chinese.
With whom these the uh Iranians have
very close relations.
So, we've we've held off so far.
Um
but the Israeli goal, because they
didn't knock out the the nuclear sites
on day one or day two,
is now to change the entire regime. Now,
one of the reasons why we might be
seeing this hubris right now is because
whether you like the Israelis or not,
you have to respect
the efficacy
of their
uh intelligence operations over the past
year or so.
This this thing with the pagers against
uh against uh Hezbollah,
absolute brilliance.
Absolutely brilliant long-term
operation, lots of moving parts, and it
was completely successful.
You have to
appreciate the way they have
completely taken out the Hezbollah
leadership. You have to appreciate the
way they worked with the Turks, and the
Turks and the Israelis hate each other.
But they worked together to overthrow
the Assad government in Syria.
So, I think the Israelis are coming off
a string of wins.
But in this case, they bit off a little
more than they could chew,
and now they're turning to the United
States for assistance.
Hm.
Do you think they did bite off more than
they can chew? Cuz they seem to be
chewing it pretty well. You look at the
Iranian response, they started off with
200 missiles, and now we're down to
about 10 missiles, a 90% drop.
I don't know if they've Would you agree
like
they haven't bitten off more than they
can chew unless they're looking for a
regime change, which is a possible cuz
I look at the regime change is a either
an if it's become an objective, that's
pretty scary. If it's just a a
nice-to-have, you know, we we our
objective is to
destroy the nuclear program.
But if we collapse the regime, that's a
great bonus, but it's not an objective.
We don't have to achieve that. Uh
I think that the what that I think
that's what makes the difference on
whether they bit off more than they
could chew or not yet. Would you agree?
I would agree. One of the things that I
think we haven't really calculated yet
is how far the Iranians are willing to
go
um
apart from the battlefield.
Again, one of these situations where
whether you like Iran or not, whether
you respect Iran or not, whether you
side with Iran or not, the historical
fact is that the the Iranians commit
acts of terrorism around the world. They
have against the United States and
against a slew of other countries.
So, if your goal is regime change now,
and the Iranian government calculates
that it cannot defeat the Israelis,
I would bet money on the fact that the
Iranians then turn to terrorism. So,
rather than to fight the Israelis on the
battlefield,
how do you protect every diplomatic uh
facility that you have around the world?
How do you protect every Jewish cultural
center around the world? Are we going to
see repeats of what we saw in the 1990s
in Argentina, for example? Are we going
to see embassy bombings? Are we going to
see kidnappings of prominent Jewish
businessmen, let's say?
Or what does it mean for the United
States? There was a There was an
incident in the 1990s where
uh the United States had been in some
sort of a skirmish with uh the Iranians,
and the Iranian response was to murder
seven American oil workers in Karachi,
Pakistan. How do you protect against
something like that? You can't. So, if
the if the Israelis
are are serious about regime change.
By God, they better accomplish it soon.
Or they're in for something bad
outside of the battlefield.
Beyond the
the closing or the attempted closing of
the Strait of Hormuz, cuz that would
obviously I want to say the
global economy but severely harm it, but
it could get a lot worse than that and
that is striking US interests and
European interests around the world and
that could lead to global
destabilization. And as you said, China
and Russia wants to stand idle, you
know, Russia
and I think it runs under Russia's
nuclear umbrella at one point. They also
have a defense pact. China and
Iran is part of BRICS. China and Iran
have a lot of business relations. So I
think if they're looking for regime
change and it becomes an existential
threat for Khamenei,
it could end up being very ugly for the
world cuz right now the world is
dismissing the impact this could have on
the economy. The markets are doing
relatively well
and the world seems to be moving on, but
it could get a lot of a lot worse if
Iran is not given an out.
I think you're exactly right. I think
that is exactly right and I'm so glad
that you brought up the Straits of
Hormuz. I should have written myself a
little note to bring this up.
Many many of your viewers I think are
probably too young to remember when the
Iranians tried to close the Straits of
Hormuz in the in the mid-1980s. Ronald
Reagan was president of the United
States at the time. And
what Reagan did was unprecedented in our
relations with Persian Gulf countries.
He ordered the US Navy into the Strait
of Hormuz to escort
oil
cargo ships
through the straits. And the straits are
very narrow. They're only about 20, what
is it, 25 km
where they go north and then south to go
around the the um
Musandam Peninsula of Oman. And so um
this was considered by the Iranians at
the time to be an act of war. Right? You
you're almost in Iranian territorial
waters, not quite, but almost. You have
to sort of thread this needle as you're
escorting these oil tankers through the
straits.
We could do that again. We might be
forced to do that again. This time, it
might be a little bit more hostile
because in 1985 and 1986, you didn't
have Iranian naval vessels firing
rockets at American ships.
We don't know if that's going to happen,
you know, in in the near future or not,
but it's something that's going to have
to be taken into consideration. So, in
the event that the Iranians
try to close the Strait of Hormuz,
the US Navy is already there,
and it will escort every one of those
oil tankers through.
Going to Russia and China, how involved
do you think they could get?
Man, this this is really the the
proverbial $64,000 question.
Um
Iranian relations with Russia and China
are far far closer than they have been
at any other point where the US and Iran
have faced conflict.
As you said correctly, Iran's a member
of BRICS now. That's a big deal.
Uh Iran falls under the Russian nuclear
umbrella. That's also a big deal that we
had didn't have to deal with in the
past.
China's the wild card here for a couple
of reasons. First of all, the Chinese
Tibet aside,
the Chinese generally do not have an
imperialist foreign policy. They've had
little border skirmishes with the
Vietnamese, a couple of skirmishes with
the Indians, but they're generally not
one to project military power abroad.
They have one permanent military base
overseas, which crazy as it might sound,
they share with the United States.
That's Camp Lemonnier in in Djibouti.
So,
on the face of things, I wouldn't expect
the Chinese to commit troops or or
planes or anything like that.
I would expect them to
commit
troops, but not combat troops. Troops to
replace Iranian troops. Let's say
Iran is in the Iranian government's in
the in danger of falling.
I could see the Chinese sending
we'll call them peacekeeping troops for
the purpose of this conversation. That
would free up Iranian troops to go fight
the fight. I could see that happening.
But, I think that the more immediate
threat to the West would be from Russia.
If the Russians aren't
overextended in Ukraine,
then it's a possibility they could they
could do something more substantive to
help the Iranians.
And do you think that significantly
weakens uh Russia's position in the war
in Ukraine? Cuz Iran is no longer
supplying weapons to Russia.
I do.
I do. And we know, of course, that the
that the Russians are reliant at least
in in part on North Korean troops. There
have been there have been rumors that
there are Chinese troops on the ground.
So, yeah, I think it would it would
weaken Russia. And the Russians have
been talking just over the last couple
of days about Odessa.
And, you know, we all thought that
Odessa was off the table. Now, maybe
it's not off the table.
Do you think they could also leverage
the negotiations? So, Putin leverages
the peace negotiations with Trump. Um
and uh China leverages the tariff
negotiations to try to twist America's
hand or Trump's hand Trump's arm into
forcing or pressuring Israel to stop the
war.
That's a great question. And I think the
answer is yes. And I think I think Putin
I I Putin knows Trump better than Trump
knows Putin.
And I think Putin understands that Trump
is
motivated motivated by the prospect of
of a grand
deal, a grand, you know, overarching
agreement. An agreement that might
include
Ukraine and tariffs and Iran and
whatever else
Putin might be interested in at any
given time.
Uh I think it's a way to sort of suck
Trump in.
Yes.
Mhm. Another way of looking at it, just
thought of it now, is that Trump this
could be Trump adding a
good card to his hand by
adding a piece in Iran as part of the
the chips that um Trump could offer
Russia in the negotiations. So, that
could be that could work in Trump's
advantage. So, Israel, one could argue,
not saying I agree with it, but one
could argue that Israel is somehow, at
least for now, doing a favor for the US.
It helps Trump if they reach a deal now.
If Trump reaches a deal now with Iran,
uh Trump could declare victory. The US
not get involved. They got a deal with
Iran. Um if that deal played a role in
Trump's negotiations with Putin,
it gave him leverage there.
So, that could end up being a positive
for the US.
And on the other hand, if this war does
drag on, if they are looking for regime
change, I think that's a loss for
literally every party involved.
I couldn't agree more.
Let's break down I'm going to read out
an analysis here and get your thoughts
on it. It's a long one. I don't know if
I'll read it all, but it's an
interesting analysis. I might break it
down into different parts and get your
thoughts on it. And that's Israel's
success with this operation. She's been
um
pretty outstanding to see.
So, Israel's preemptive military
operation against Iran appears to have
severely crippled Iran's missile command
structure and its capacity to retaliate
following a complex deception campaign
led by Israeli intelligence. So, let's
go through that one first. So, do you
think the the deception that happened
beforehand, including Trump talking
about a peace deal, he thinks that an
agreement will be reached? I think
Netanyahu promised
Netanyahu uh
pretended that his son had a wedding or
maybe his son didn't have wedding and
pretended he's going to have a meeting
in the US. Do you think all these were
part of a disinformation campaign
against Iran? And there's also been
rumors that I'm not sure if it's in the
analysis, that
Um okay, this this is on as well.
According to sources familiar with the
operation, Mossad initiated a targeted
disinformation effort days before the
strike using falsified communications
through Iranian channels that triggered
what appeared to be an emergency
meeting. The ruse successfully drew the
entire leadership of Iran's IRGC Air
Space Force, including the commander
general, his deputies, and key technical
personnel into a fortified bunker
outside Tehran where they were taken
out. Um
First,
do you think that's all plausible?
Second, what does that say about Israeli
intelligence? That just seems
insanely concerning for any enemy of the
Israel.
There is no better intelligence service
on Earth than the Mossad.
They are the best. Even at the CIA, we
used to just shake our heads in in
wonderment sometimes at some of the
things that the Mossad accomplished.
Look at the Look at the the the pager
operations for a moment.
I I gave I gave an interview to a
Russian network after this operation.
And the the questions were completely
loaded.
Like, isn't this a crime against
humanity?
Yes.
Uh should they be punished? And I said,
you have to understand
from the perspective of an intelligence
officer, this plan was a stroke of
genius.
Can you imagine
the work that went into reverse
engineering the supply chain
for for for pagers?
Not only do you have to identify
what kind of pagers Hezbollah
Hezbollah's leadership is using,
but you have to reverse engineer the
entire supply chain
either take over manufacturing
or intercept the manufactured pieces,
load bombs or plastic or whatever they
used into every single unit making sure
that they continued to work properly.
And then
have them distributed to the right
people once they got to Lebanon. This
This had to be years in the making and
it had to be an operation where
literally everything went right at every
step of the way.
So when I hear reports that
that they used
falsified communications to to
essentially lure the Iranian
intelligence leadership to one location
so they could hit it and take it out
take them out.
Absolutely, I believe it 100%. They're
that good.
How are they that good for such a small
country?
Because they can't lose. If they if they
lose, they cease to exist.
You know, in the United States sometimes
you do something stupid, you make a
stupid decision or or your policy makers
make a stupid
decision and you end up being bogged
down in a conflict like Afghanistan that
lasts for 20 years. Okay, you learn a
lesson, you move on. If the Israelis
lose
they cease to exist.
And so they can't lose. They'll do
literally anything
to ensure victory.
That's why we we
we toss around terms like war crimes or
crimes against humanity. Yes, often
times they are war crimes or crimes
against humanity and yes, in a perfect
world they would be prosecuted in some
international venue.
But they're not
because they don't care what the rest of
the world thinks. It's all about
survival.
You've also seen the reports I'm sure
about a drone factory and explosive
drone factory within Iran. Do you think
that's possible not just trucks being
smuggled in, similar to what Ukraine did
in Russia, but an actual factory within
Iran, as well as um Mossad commandos in
the country?
Yeah, I believe it. I had I had a
conversation with a with a former CIA
colleague of mine just a few days ago.
We talked about that.
And I said uh
I said the balls that the that the
Israelis have,
they've essentially moved intelligence
operations into Iran proper and set up
like they own the place.
And he said, "You know, that's the
thing. It's so
it's so gutsy
that even the Iranians probably thought,
'Well, nobody would have the guts to
actually come here and open up a
factory.'
Right? But the Israelis did.
The Israelis did. One of the first
things that I said, as soon as the first
wave of Israeli missiles were flying,
was that the Israelis have an incredible
network of spies in Iran.
A network that dwarfs what any of us had
previously thought.
And conversely, the Iranians
have to clean up their society because
they are utterly and totally infiltrated
by Israeli intelligence.
It does feel like it's a movie. And and
I can't even imagine how Khamenei, the
supreme leader, would be feeling right
now to have his name mentioned a couple
of times by Trump saying that he stopped
Israel from assassinating him. Or I
think Trump's official said that. And
Netanyahu, there was an ad that came
with a chessboard. I'm not sure if
you've seen it. An Israeli ad that
hinted that Khamenei could be next. And
I think Netanyahu said that if we get
rid of Khamenei, we might win the war.
I'm paraphrasing here.
And plus, all his close advisers are
gone. There's barely any left. That must
And to make it even worse, it reminds me
of the movie uh
I forgot what it's called, the one with
Leonardo DiCaprio, where you just don't
know who to trust anymore.
Uh Jack Nicholson was the main actor.
He's the the the leader of some mafia
group and he just was at a position
The Departed. Yeah, and he he he started
questioning each one of his close con-
confidants about who is the rat. And
then it it gets even more complex where
Jack Nicholson was a rat for another
agency. So, this has feeling like could
the former president Ahmadinejad been a
rat? It just it would get into his head
a psychological warfare to another level
for the supreme leader.
Oh my god, yes. You know, there's really
there's a famous Israeli story where in
the 1960s
they hired a
the Mossad hired a a guy. He had
volunteered actually to um to join
Mossad and he didn't make the cut.
Uh but it turned out that his Arabic was
so good. It was native Arabic,
unaccented Arabic that they later
approached him and said, "Hey, remember
you tried to apply with us? We have a
job for you." They sent him to Syria
with money and secure communications.
He so ingratiated himself with the
Syrian leadership
that
that in 1965 he was he was considered
for the position of deputy minister of
defense
of Syria.
And the whole time he's an Israeli
citizen.
He's Jewish
pretending to be a Syrian Arab.
And he's reporting back to uh to Mossad.
He made a mistake one one night. Um the
Russians secretly went to the Syrians
and said, "You've got a mole. We're not
sure who it is, but there's a mole." And
so, the Russians triangulated his
transmissions and they were able to
narrow it down to a couple of houses.
The Syrians finally raided the house and
arrested him and he was he was hanged in
the public square, but he's a he's a
great hero in Israel today.
Um what's his name? Eli Cohen? Something
like that.
Um his his widow is still is still
living.
Uh but th- this is what the Israelis do.
When I was at the CIA, the Israelis did
an operation that was just brilliant.
This is This is the period where, you
know, you wanted to move a satellite, it
would take 6 months to move the
satellite, right? And the Israelis
really, really wanted to know what was
going on in the port of Benghazi.
And so, an Israeli intelligence officer
called the harbor master in Benghazi and
said, "Hi, I'm a French businessman and
I represent the interests of a group of
other French businessmen. And because we
invest so much money,
we need to know exactly what ships are
in port and what the bills of lading
say."
Uh so, we're looking for somebody we can
hire as a consultant. Do you know
anybody that would like to be a
consultant because we have so much
money, we can pay pretty much anything."
And the harbor master, of course, says,
"Yeah, I'll I'll be a consultant for
you."
And they said, "Okay, we're going to
call you every morning and then you tell
us which ships are in port and you tell
us everything that the ship is
carrying."
And so, he did.
And this went on for years. And they
would wire some money into his account,
you know, every few days.
And they didn't need to move satellites.
They didn't need to to infiltrate the
the harbor master's office on the
ground. They already had the harbor
master himself.
And so, for years they knew when Syrian
ships were in Benghazi, when they had
when they had
weapons or ammunition on them, they had
everything they ever wanted.
And all it took was a phone call. That
was it.
Reminds me of the way you can easily
plant a virus within any system by just
coming up with the research that was
done. But you just drop a USB in a
parking lot and someone will eventually
pick it up. Write something on it. Come
find out that someone will pick it up
and place it in his makes it seem how
easy it is, especially for for an
intelligence like Mossad, to be able to
infiltrate pretty much anything.
But they just took it to another level.
There's another report as well that
Israel's using AI to be able to spot
whenever So it came out today whenever
Iran was about to fire missiles and the
rocket launchers have been prepared,
Israel through AI was able to tell which
specific movements
were the preparation for a missile to be
launched and strike those missile
launchers either before being launched
or right after being launched. And that
continues to deplete Iran's capacity. Um
which is again just another another
crazy capability if if true. Um
So we continue next piece of analysis
get your thoughts on.
There was absolutely no one alive to
give the command to strike back. That
was after the Israel strike
struck. So then they struck that bunker
when they got that important meeting of
all the
senior commanders. Moments before the
strike began that bunker was hit in a
precision air strike before Israel's
main strike started. Eliminating Iran's
top missile command. Israeli officials
say the goal was clear, prevent the
launch of what was believed to be over a
thousand ballistic missiles aimed at
Israeli territory. There was no one
alive to give the command to strike
back. Immediately afterward Israel
launched a sweeping campaign across Iran
and other strategic areas hitting
missile sites, infrastructure and air
defense. The operation had been years as
you said had been years in preparation.
Mossad sleeper cells embedded in Iran
since as early as 2007, decades had
smuggled hundreds of drones and military
equipment into the country using
commercial trucks. These assets remained
dormant until activated in the hours
before the operation. How effective when
you take out military commanders? I've
had two different arguments being made.
One is like, you know, similar to when
you mow the grass, new grass will grow.
The other one's like, when you kill a
commander at that at those positions of
that seniority, there's a lot of
know-how and also a lot of
clout and respect that they have. When
that is eliminated, it severely hampers
the ability for Iran to fire those
missiles. The people that make the
decision to fire the missiles have just
been
targeted. Um
is it really that difficult for
an organization like the IRGC to be able
to respond once commanders were were
assassinated at such speed?
Not necessarily.
But it does delay the decision-making.
And that's what the Israelis were
counting on. You know, IRGC is like any
other organization, whether governmental
or non-governmental. You take out the
leadership and there are going to be
others that immediately rise up to
positions of leadership. I I was joking
with a friend the other day that
that we killed at least a dozen number
threes in al-Qaeda in the in the period
that that I was still in the CIA
fighting al-Qaeda. There's always going
to be somebody else to take those
positions. But what the Israelis were
counting on here
was that it would take a day or two or
five
to replace those commanders. And that
extra period of time what is what
allowed the Israelis to to take out even
more of the leadership or more of the
hardware that the leadership would have
used to to respond to the initial
Israeli attack.
And I'll continue the rest of it and
then kind of make some of the points
you've made already. As the assault
began, pre-positioned drones were
launched to disable Iran's air defense
grid and blind its radar systems. That's
the drone that either from the factory
and or the trucks that were smuggled in.
Which I've heard that smuggling in
trucks is relatively easy.
Oh, yeah.
Are you in Are you in Israel or here?
Oh, that's an ambulance.
No,
no, I'm in Washington.
Okay, okay.
I'm
Making sure you're okay. Sirens are
It's probably a military parade. No, I'm
kidding.
Um so,
Yeah.
So, so Iran has a massive border.
Smuggling people or equipment in
is relatively easy. When you look at
countries like the US, which is
obviously more significantly more
advanced than Iran, not being able in
Europe not being able to deal with
immigrants, illegal immigrants, and
wanting to build a wall, um then the
argument could be made that Iran's large
border, and especially the the the
destabilization of Syria and other
countries around Iran, makes it very
difficult for Iran to secure that
border.
And that's a massive advantage for
Mossad.
You you are 100% correct. If if you look
well the the border with Afghanistan is
essentially unprotected. It's just too
it's too rugged, it's too mountainous,
it's too much of a desert. You just
can't control that gigantic a border. In
Balochistan, so we're talking about
southeastern Iran and southwestern
Pakistan,
uh
not only is that border almost
impossible to protect, but it's also
where separatist groups live on the
Pakistani side.
And so smuggling is a very big problem.
But smuggling it is also a problem in
the Gulf. It's something that I saw
myself. You would think that it would be
utterly protected and protectable
uh in the Gulf because the Gulf
countries are so advanced and so
sophisticated. But
if you go out you walk every morning to
the to the harbor in Kuwait City, for
example, or in Manama, the capital of
Bahrain, or even in in Dubai or Sharjah,
which are both right on the water. Um
and you see
hundreds and hundreds of dhows. Dhows, d
h o w s, are those those old-style
wooden boats that are that are uh common
in the Persian Gulf. And normally you
see them docked in the morning with
fruits and vegetables and fish and
shrimp, and they're just independent
uh fishermen, smugglers, but fishermen
selling their wares early in the
morning. Well,
nobody even bothers to inspect those
boats. Nobody bothers to pay any
attention to them.
And so, how easy would it be
to put drones on them or to put
missiles? I would venture to say it
would be very easy, and it would
complement
the the smuggling operations that are
taking place in places like Balochistan,
for example.
So, if if the Iranians are worried about
smuggling, and they're focused on
Balochistan with this
strange
separatist group,
the
Balochistan People's Liberation Army,
whatever it's called.
Um
their their
attention is is uh
diverted from the Gulf. And I wouldn't
be surprised at all if some of those
things got in
right under their noses from the Gulf.
So, we continue. And by the way, I just
want to give a shout-out to Open Source
Intel for for this analysis.
As the assault began, pre-positioned
drones, we talked about this. It's
estimated that over 15% of Iran's
ballistic missile arsenal was destroyed
in the opening wave. So, that's just the
missiles, not the launchers. Nearly all
critical air defense systems in and
around Tehran were neutralized in the
first hour, which obviously we're seeing
with Israel's complete air dominance.
At the same time, Israeli strikes
targeted top nuclear scientists involved
in the regime's advanced enrichment
program.
Iran's ability to respond collapsed.
What was expected to be a massive
retaliation was reduced to just 150
ballistic missiles launched 20 hours
after the Israeli operation began.
Spread across three waves, a fraction of
what we had anticipated. And I remember
I was talking to a former It was a
former intelligence officer in in
wildest we're doing it live. We're
talking live. And while the the Iranian
response was happening, and he said,
"Mario, you know, he was um speaking
about, you know, he's warning about
Iran's capabilities, not to
underestimate Iran. And while the
retaliation was happening, he's like, he
I expect for this to really make a
difference. I expect at least 1,000
missiles to be launched by Iran, if not
more."
And we saw
it hasn't even hit 1,000 with with 4
days in, and it's now dropped to about
10 at a time. Um so, what does that say
about Iran's capabilities or lack
thereof after Israel's attack?
And could Iran Does Iran have certain
capabilities other than
um going guerrilla style and targeting
the Strait of Hormuz or going, you know,
the terrorism path. Does it have other
military capabilities that we haven't
seen yet that they're kind of holding
back, holding back trying to get some
sort of deal?
No.
I don't think so. I think the Israelis
are so superior
to the Iranians militarily that in this
case what we see is what we get. There
there is no secret weapon.
Uh, there is no second stash of uh, of
missiles or um, or drones or
launchers or or anything. As you said,
and I think this is absolutely correct,
the fact that they can no longer defend
Tehran
says a great deal.
And then last thing it says is the the
um, an attack of um, 40% of missile
launches were also um, destroyed with
Israel's attack. Um, now what happens if
Israel goes down the the
um, something that no one would have
expected a week ago and that's
assassinating the leader himself. Would
that work in Israel's advantage or that
could that backfire?
No, I think it would backfire. One of
the things that I've learned over the
years is that um,
Ayatollah Khamenei is very popular,
personally popular.
And um,
I think that to to plunge Iran into
even a temporary chaos where where a new
supreme leader would have to be chosen,
uh,
does nothing but
but bring the Iranian people together
and unify them.
Uh,
when I when I read the same articles
that you read saying that Donald Trump
apparently had talked the uh, Israelis
out of assassinating uh, Ayatollah
Khamenei, I thought that was
quite
fortuitous.
I think that would be a step too far. It
doesn't And it doesn't get the Israelis
anything. It's not like he's a military
commander, you know, moving divisions
from here to there to to the third
place. He's just a
He's just a figure. He's a He's a you
know, theocratic figure and a rallying
point for Iranians.
Taking that away doesn't really do
anything militarily.
But isn't that a crossing international
law because you're not, as far as I
understand, you're not meant to target
the leader of another nation-state
during war. And that would also put
Netanyahu's life in danger as well. Is
that another concern? Not that you know,
Israel's already crossed a few lines
with the pager attack
and striking the TV station.
Um but that seems to be a much
bigger red line.
I I would agree with that. I think it's
it's too much even for Donald Trump,
it's too much
to target another leader.
talking about President Trump, um how
involved do you think he was? Do you
think he was he knew about the attack
that the the the um
the details, strategies, and and the
plan, Israel's plan, Israel's objective,
Israel's targets beforehand?
Did he give the okay, or do you think he
was caught blindsided? Blindsided.
I think he was probably informed in
advance. That would have been the norm
uh to as a courtesy to inform the United
States uh that such an attack was was
occurring. But I'll tell you something
that the Israelis do.
Um
the United States does not work hand in
glove with the Israelis at all times. Uh
contrary to to popular belief. When I
was
when I was still in the CIA, my last job
at headquarters was as executive
assistant to the CIA's deputy director
for operations. And we were preparing to
fight uh the Iraq war. We were preparing
to cross the border in the coming days.
So, this is four or five days before we
actually initiated hostilities. And the
Israelis came to us
and said,
"We really want to be a part of this
attack."
And we said, "Absolutely
not. There can't be any Israeli
involvement, especially on the ground.
It'll unify the Arabs against us.
You have to stay out of it."
Well, within 24 hours,
all of Iraq's
um electrical towers in the western
desert began tipping over.
These were you know, we've all seen
electrical towers that go for miles and
miles and miles and you see the the
cables running along the top. The ones
in Iraq had three
legs, right? So, three legs, let me turn
my hand there like that. Three legs to
keep them up. The Israelis would blow up
one leg and the tower would tip over.
And I remember the deputy director
saying, "Those damn Israelis, we told
them to stay out of it. But they so
wanted to attack Iraq
just in a small way, just to be a part
of it,
that they disregarded everything that we
said."
So, I think in this case they they
wouldn't have wanted to really anger the
United States. Uh we had already told
them we wouldn't attack Iran for them.
But I think they probably
gave us a heads-up that this was coming.
And usually a heads-up like that comes 3
4 5 hours before the actual event.
Why wouldn't they listen to the US?
That's surprising to me. I thought the
US had a lot more influence over Israel
considering that they're the support
that they're biggest ally, they're
supporting them a lot in the UN, but
also militarily and financially.
A lot of it has to do with Benjamin
Netanyahu as a person, as a leader.
Uh Netanyahu is incredibly
arrogant.
Uh and believes that not only does he
know better than every American
president,
but that because he lives it every day
that that he lives in this dangerous
neighborhood called the Middle East um
that he understands better than any
American president could understand.
And it infuriates him that president
after president after president has
refused to attack Iran on behalf of
Israel.
And so
I think that he calculated that if he
acted unilaterally
the United States eventually would be
forced into
moving into Iran to support the the
Israeli position.
And and we might even get there. You
know,
Donald Trump is so hard to read because
he'll he'll say one thing and then he'll
say exactly the opposite thing, you
know, sometimes an hour later, sometimes
in the same sentence.
And so you really don't know what
American policy is. And I think that
Netanyahu believes that he can influence
whatever that policy ends up being.
Interesting. Um
Do Do you think Trump is genuinely
looking for a peace deal right now or
that ship has sailed?
You've got Israel talking about
potential regime change and operation I
think is rising lion and potentially
targeting Khamenei which and they
targeted the chief negotiator as well.
So if they're looking for negotiations,
shouldn't he be the only one that that
is left alive even more important than
the supreme leader, not as important but
second after the supreme leader if
they're looking for a deal. Um do you
think there's a genuine disconnect
between Israel and the US or is it all
part of a strategy where
Israel makes it seem like they're
willing to go all the way to give Trump
more leverage in the negotiations.
I think the latter is probably the case.
I have a friend at the White House who
told me to never underestimate
Donald Trump's desire to win a Nobel
Peace Prize.
He's still angry that Barack Obama has a
Nobel Peace Prize.
And And why he initiated
talks with the North Koreans, for
example. That's why he keeps talking
about a grand deal. That's why he said
that he could influence the Russians
into ending the Ukraine war within 24
hours of taking the oath of office.
Uh none of those things have happened
yet. But um but I think he really is
optimistic about some grand deal that is
going to make him the peacemaker
of the Middle East.
Now, if there is some kind of a deal,
it's going to be with a rump Iran.
You know, maybe it's it's going to be
with
some temporary government
who that takes over after the the
collapse of the present one. Who knows?
Who knows what it's going to look like.
But I think he he really believes he can
make a deal and he should be rewarded
for it.
That's a great North Star to have if
he's really aiming for that. It's a
great objective and that's a good, you
know, good news.
Um which goes to the second second part
of the question which you already hinted
on is how much influence does he have
over Israel? And kind of links to it
Yeah, another question is how involved
do you think the US will get?
Ooh.
Um
I think he does have influence over
Israel, but not as much as he probably
thinks he does. Benjamin Netanyahu is
very stubborn and is very, very willing
to act unilaterally.
Uh
Disagreements with American presidents
have never held him back in the past.
Um
Yeah, you know, the second part of your
question is the one that I think is is
unanswerable. We We really don't know
what it's going to look like.
We really don't know. Because we haven't
really heard from the Saudis, the
Kuwaitis, the Emiratis, the Bahrainis.
We haven't heard from The Jordanians
haven't said a word. The Egyptians
haven't said a word. I think they're all
panicked at the idea of what this might
look like at the end. And so they're
waiting waiting to see how it plays out
before making their own positions known.
Yeah, I think Saudi's position is really
tricky cuz Saudi would benefit from a
weaker Iran, but also I think Saudi
would lose more and would be more at
risk from a destabilized Iran or regime
change. How much influence does Saudi
have and also how strong is Saudi
militarily?
Oh, no. If
If you compare it to let's say Israel.
Not that they're they're not enemies and
they're talking about obviously
being part of the peace accords, but
Sure.
putting that aside, I'm just curious how
strong that other military power is.
It's not. It's not. There There's an
ongoing joke in the Middle East that
that it it's hard to find any Saudis in
the Saudi military.
They're all Pakistanis. All of them.
Uh the only ones who are Saudis are the
generals.
The leaders.
Literally. I had a I had a great friend
when I was living in Bahrain. I was I
was
assigned to the State Department at the
American Embassy in Bahrain. And I had a
friend who was the He was a Kuwaiti
American who was the head of American
Express for the Gulf. And he got drafted
by the Kuwaiti military.
And so
I said, "I thought you were Kuwaiti.
You're drafted into the Kuwaiti
military." He said, "Oh, no. It's a big
joke."
So, he goes to Kuwait. On the first day,
he said every everybody was there. It
was about 30 people and about a third of
them were sheikhs.
And then the second day, about half of
them showed up.
And the third day, he was the only
Kuwaiti who showed up
for training. And then after that, he
just quit.
He just walk out, fly back to Bahrain.
So, what they do is they just replace
all these people with Pakistani
volunteers.
And that's who fights the wars for the
Saudis and the Kuwaitis and and others
in the Gulf.
not that it obviously is relevant to
this discussion um cuz Saudi's not an
enemy of Israel, but Saudi doesn't stand
a chance in front of Israel either.
Not a chance. Not a prayer.
Egypt? Egypt?
Uh the Egyptians are different. Hosni
Mubarak used to say
that Egypt was safe safe just because of
its overwhelming population.
Egypt has what?
180 million people?
So compared to
9.8 million for Israel.
Nuclear weapons aside,
the Egyptians are perfectly fine just
the way they are.
How about Turkey? What role does Turkey
play in all this? We talked about how
Turkey and Israel despite hating one
another, they
you know they work together when it
comes to Syria. What about in this case?
Turkey's really an enigma in this whole
thing.
For many many years, for decades, the
Turks and the Israelis had very close
relations, very close diplomatic
relations, close military relations. And
then President Erdogan flipped that
about 15 or 20 years ago. Conversely,
the Greeks had traditionally very close
relations with the Arabs to the point
where
all of the Palestinian terrorist groups
Popular Front for the Liberation of
Palestine
uh
PFLP General Command, Democratic Front
for the Liberation of Palestine, the Abu
Nidal Organization, they all had a
presence in Athens. So if the Turks are
going to be with the Israelis, the
Greeks are going to be with the Arabs.
Then the Turks flipped.
And they began challenging the Israelis.
Well, if the Turks are going to be
pro-Arab, then the Greeks felt they had
to flip.
So now the Greeks and the Cypriots are
pro-Israel.
And the Turks are pro-Arab.
And they're like watching each other to
see what the other one's going to do
next.
But
with that said,
the Turks and the Israelis work together
to overthrow Bashar al-Assad.
And they work together very smoothly and
very quickly.
I know a lot of Middle East watchers
because we've spent our entire adult
lives watching these issues develop. I
don't think anybody expected Assad to
fall apart in 1 week.
And I think in a great part it was
because of the Turks.
Um how how capable is the Turkish
military when you compare it to somebody
to Israel?
It's quite capable.
It's very large. It's very well trained
and remember it's a part of NATO. So it
has
almost exclusively
American French and British weapons.
Yeah, there's one interesting thing
there.
One of the things the Saudis used to do
just for the purpose of maintaining good
relations with the Russians and the
Chinese. The The Saudis are almost
exclusively
the users of American weapons and
weapons systems, right? And American
jets.
But they'll buy
Russian systems or Chinese systems and
then never take them out of the crates.
They'll buy them so they can maintain
good trade relations with the Russians
and the Chinese and just keep them in a
warehouse somewhere never to be used.
So they've got the equipment. They just
don't do anything with it.
The Turks on the other hand have Western
equipment
but then also have been dabbling in
Russian equipment just to maintain good
relations with the Russians. So I think
the Turks are very well provided for and
very capable.
Politics is just so
confusingly interested.
Interesting. Um
but Turkish capability military
capability should not be ignored and
again, I know this is not even a worst
case scenario. I think it's not
something that should even be discussed
but just for for for people to
understand the strength of Israel in the
region,
does Turkey stand a chance against
Israel militarily?
Again,
nuclear weapons aside,
Nuclear weapons and NATO aside.
And NATO aside, yeah, the the Turks are
the Turks are tough and strong and mean
and very capable. Yes.
Interesting. I know you said
keep in mind, too, if I can make one one
other point, keep in mind, too, that the
Turks are very well skilled in in
guerrilla warfare, anti-guerrilla
warfare, because of so many years of
fighting the the PKK.
Yeah, true.
Um
Hezbollah Hezbollah Hezbollah surprised
me when I was talking to the IDF
spokesperson 2 days ago, and that was
one of the biggest surprises for the IDF
is that they expected Hezbollah to be
one of the first proxies or the only
proxy left along with the Houthis to
respond,
and they didn't. Um I was told that they
faced pressure from the the day after
the Israeli attack, the Lebanese
government, with the support of Saudi
and the French, um
warned them that they will interfere if
Hezbollah backs Iran.
So, does that mean that Iran's grip over
their most important proxies loosening,
or is that just strategic so Iran has a
final card they can play?
I think it's a combination of the two,
actually. Um
on the one hand, the Iranians still have
Hezbollah as a proxy. On the other hand,
they can't supply Hezbollah anymore,
because Assad's gone.
Couple that with the fact that Hezbollah
was was decapitated
by these Israeli operations. I still
shake my head like, what an incredible
absolutely incredible intelligence
operation this was. I I still can't even
fathom the work that went into
decapitating Hezbollah like they did,
but
remember, not only did they do this this
Pager operation, they also detonated
explosives in cell phones, and they
bombed Hezbollah and took out the
leadership, the second-level leadership,
and the third-level leadership.
So, for all intents and purposes, at
least for the next next 6 months,
there is no such thing as Hezbollah. Not
really.
It's going to have to reconstitute
itself.
But, they're in no position right now
whatsoever
to launch anything against the Israelis,
especially when they can't be
resupplied.
Exactly. I I think What does that mean
for Lebanon? If this is true, which I
think it is,
is that a positive thing for Lebanon cuz
now they're forced to be more
pro-Western and Western countries
countries that have been aligned with
the West have prospered more in the
Middle East.
Yeah, I I think so. I hate to say it
like that, but but yeah, I think that's
probably the bottom line. Lebanon is a
failed state. It's a basket case.
It shouldn't be because it has a
remarkable constitution, one that gives
equal authority to to all of the
religious groups in the country.
But,
it doesn't work.
It doesn't work, and you have
essentially a state within a state in
the form of Hezbollah that has its own
foreign policy, that has its own
military.
Excuse me.
And and it doesn't take orders from the
central government in Beirut.
Well, now that's been pushed aside.
And so, I think that this is a period
where we're going to go into a period of
at least 6 months
of an uneasy peace
in Lebanon, where the central government
is not going to have to worry about
cleaning up a mess
that Hezbollah creates for it on the
southern border.
And then if they pass that 6 months, it
could lead to a period of prosperity.
Obviously, it just depends on so many
factors in the Middle East. Talking
about these factors, I'm trying to
understand the regional impact this
could have. The risks of a radiation
leak, is that a genuine risk and could
that impact neighboring countries,
including uh Dubai where I'm at now?
Cuz I've also heard by experts that the
um the nuclear enrichment that Iran is
doing um the stage that it's at now,
it's not like a nuclear,
um, reactor that we saw in Chernobyl or
in Japan, for example. So, that risk,
for example, for countries like the UAE
is not really that significant.
I think it's not that significant. We've
We've seen, um,
We've seen reports that are at odds with
one another over a leak coming out of
the the very first wave of Israeli
attacks. Um, that there that there was a
leak
uh, yesterday were heard, there is not a
leak, there was an IAEA uh, group on the
ground saying that they can't detect a
leak. In the event that there was a
leak,
um, I don't think Dubai
would be, um, affected because it's not
like Chernobyl, for example,
where entire swaths had to be, you know,
depopulated.
Or or areas that
Cuz countries like Dubai, if if it's not
a radiation leak, how about, um, the
UAE, uh, Qatar, Saudi being targeted by
Iran? So, instead of Iran targeting the
US cuz they don't want the US to get
involved, seemingly, um, they would
instead target Israeli allies or US
allies as a way to put pressure on
Israel. Is that a possibility? Cuz I did
speak to someone that was based in the
in Abu Dhabi, and they said that that
was a concern when they were there years
ago that Iran could target it when there
was a lot of tension. Now, I think it's
just a whole different ballgame. Is that
a genuine concern?
I I don't think so anymore. I I would
have said the same thing from the period
where I was living in Bahrain. There was
no greater threat to the Bahrainis than
than Iran. They were obsessed with Iran,
as were the Saudis at the time, because
fully 35%
of of Saudi nationals in the Eastern
Province of Saudi Arabia are Shia
Muslims,
like uh, most Iranians are. Uh, but
today,
Iran has been just decimated over the
last few days. I don't think they pose a
threat to anybody outside of Iran, not
right now.
And uh, you know, relations have
changed, too, Mario, where
where
you know, the the Saudis and the
Iranians at any given moment were on the
brink of war, right? It It things could
change like flipping a switch. And
that's just not the case anymore. Under
Under Mohammed bin Salman
and listen, we can have a whole
conversation about Mohammed bin Salman
and whether he's a great leader or a
deranged maniac, you know, or something
in between,
we could have that talk. But he's
actually played relations with Iran very
smartly.
And so, there's been this uh this
detente between the two countries.
They've exchanged ambassadors again.
Relations seem to be good and getting
better. And of course, whatever the
Saudis do, they drag the Bahrainis along
with them. The Kuwaitis generally sit
out these things. They're unaligned. Um
nonaligned. Uh the Emiratis and the
Saudis work very, very closely together
on these issues, especially surrounding
Iran.
And the Qataris
you know, the Qataris are always just
going to be
the Qataris.
They're just going to be independent of
everybody else.
I've got news for you. It just happened
now. Um
a massive oil tanker in the Strait of
Hormuz, it's called the Adeline, uh went
up in flames after colliding with Front
Eagle in the Gulf of Oman right next to
planet's busiest oil
artery. 24 crew had to be pulled to
safety as the upper deck burnt. Front
Eagle was carrying 2 million barrels of
Iraqi crude oil to China. Adeline was
empty but still ignited chaos. Officials
have said it wasn't security related but
with electronic interference, naval
buildups, and a full-blown regional
conflict above the waterline, safe
passage is getting dicey. Tehran's
hinted at blocking the straits. So, we
don't know if it's Iran or not. So, Iran
is not taking responsibility, but
we're starting to edge closer to that
you know, kind of worst-case scenario of
Iran getting desperate. And that's why
the concern goes back to the initial
part of the discussion is that if we if
Iran gets desperate, this could really
get ugly regionally. That's why I asked
the question is could they strike these
allies? Is when you put Khamenei's life
in danger, you know when when we talked
about President Putin and whether he
would use a nuclear weapon. Most people
agreed that that's unlikely.
And obviously NATO calculated it as such
as well. They kept pushing that line. Um
and one of the arguments is if his life
one of the reasons he would use a
nuclear weapon is is if his life was in
danger. Khamenei's life is in danger.
Could that lead to Iran using a nuclear
weapon? I know they don't have one, but
could they have a dirty bomb or maybe a
small nuclear weapon that they could,
you know, kind of transport to another
to to to It doesn't have to be Israel,
just another country, a US ally, maybe
the US through a briefcase. Could they
have some sort of plan for a scenario
like this that could be very very ugly
for the world? Or will Israel have so
much intelligence that they would know
about it in advance and calculate for
that?
Yeah, I I I can't see the Iranians
developing even even a dirty bomb
related to the nuclear program.
Um
and even if they had a a nuclear bomb or
some sort of small nuclear device,
there's no delivery system for it. They
just haven't developed a delivery system
yet. You know, the the earliest
the earliest that Benjamin Netanyahu
began talking about Iran
developing a nuclear bomb, I saw this in
the New York Times the other day, was an
interview he gave in 1992
saying that Iran is 6 months away from a
nuclear bomb.
1992,
he's been screaming this
for decades.
Decades.
And it's just it's never been true. As
recently as March of this year, Tulsi
Gabbard, the the American Director of
National Intelligence, testified on
Capitol Hill
that the Iranians do not have a nuclear
weapons program.
They had one
that Ayatollah Khamenei
uh froze in 2003, and the consensus of
the US intelligence community, all 18
members of the US intelligence
community, is that there is no Iranian
nuclear weapons program.
So, how does that How does that
Isn't that contradicted by the IAEA
report just a day before Israel struck
Iran?
Well, not necessarily, because what the
IAEA is saying is that the Iranians had
been enriching uranium at 35%. They
upped that to 67%.
That's not weapons grade. Weapons grade
is 95%, but it's very easy to go from 67
to 95. It's very difficult to go from 25
to 95.
But, if they went from 35 to 65, which
is more difficult, or 25 to to 65,
doesn't that mean that they could have
changed their strategy, and now they're
looking to enrich it as a you know, one
Again, another argument that could be
made is
Gaddafi gave up his nuclear ambitions,
is dead.
North Korea, Kim Jong-un, did not give
up his nuclear ambitions, he's alive,
and North Korea's untouched. Um could
Khamenei looked at all of his proxies
being destroyed, Israel's threat
escalating, so then he was starting to
seek a nuclear weapon
as a way to to have that kind of
last resort of nuclear deterrence, so
Israel doesn't strike Iran. Is that a
possibility, and could that not I
wouldn't say justify, but maybe give
one reason for Israel to strike Iran, or
do you think it was all a kind of Iraqi
uh weapons of mass destruction moment
No, I think you're right. I think that
it's a possibility, and it would give
justification, actually on both sides.
It would give justification to the
Israelis to attack, but it would give
justification
to the Iranians to do whatever was
possible to protect themselves. Look at
the situation between um India and and
Pakistan.
The The consensus in the CIA was that if
there was going to be a nuclear
exchange,
it was not going to be the US and
Russia, the US and China, it was going
to be India and Pakistan.
Pakistan is Listen, I lived in Pakistan.
I worked there. I worked with Pakistan
intelligence and military officials. The
country's not stable.
It's just not.
And there's always a danger of nuclear
weapons falling into the wrong hands.
Well, the world just accepts that.
So, I think that the Iranian calculation
is that the world is just going to have
to accept that the Iranians one of these
days are going to have a nuclear bomb.
They probably don't intend to use it
offensively. It's a deterrent against
the Israelis, and I think the Iranians
genuinely believe that that is the only
thing that can keep them safe.
And you think the Israelis genuinely
believe that was an existential threat
for Israel, and they had to get rid of
it considering the narrative out of
Iran? Cuz I think there's mistakes when
it comes to this war. I feel like
there's mistakes done on both sides.
Oh, yes.
Absolutely. Absolutely. There's no
understanding of the other of the
others' position. None whatsoever.
He's a threat to me. I'm a threat to
him.
And then we just see where the cards
fall.
But I think you're right that
Is that because there's no way of them
like
there was no one that could guarantee
security for Iran and Israel for to give
them both peace of mind. Could that be a
possibility? Cuz one would look at it
one that wants to oversimplify and this
is not deep into this political world.
They'd be looking at it like, "Hey, why
can't both uh countries make an
agreement say, 'Hey, we will not uh
attack you with a nuclear weapon. You
let us build it.' Or we will build it
halfway and you let us be there. And if
we build it more, you'll stop us." It
just seems like a deal could be reached.
Right. What Why Why didn't they? Like
I know it's a lot more complex than
that. There's a lot of moving pieces
even when it goes all the way to
Ukraine, China. A lot of people
influence every single decision made,
you know, Ukraine and Russia. Ukraine is
just a you know, almost a proxy for
NATO, for example, a way to weaken
Russia. So, I just think it's way too
complicated for Iran, and then I would
link that to how much do you think
Russia and China played a role in
influencing Iran's decisions leading up
to the war.
You're right, it's complex, but that
would really be the the best outcome.
And if the United States had better
relations with with Russia and with
China, I think that would have been not
just a possibility, but a really
wonderful development in in modern
history.
Yeah, you just have these
superpowers guaranteeing
sovereignty and survivability.
Yeah, I think it's well said there. And
how about the risk of a long-term war?
Um
what are the factors you'd be looking at
right now to determine whether this will
end soon or this could end up dragging
on for 6-12 months?
Ground troops.
President Trump said yesterday the
United States has 34,000 ground troops
at nine different facilities in the
Gulf.
Um 34,000 is a lot of troops, but it's
not enough to fight a war. If the United
States began supplementing those 34,000
with another couple of hundred thousand,
then we're in for a fight, a long-term
fight. But there's no indication that
the US is at all interested in sending
ground troops to the region. And the
Israelis just don't have the
wherewithal. Remember, Israel has fewer
than 10 million people, and there are 90
million in Iran, so it it would be
suicide if the if the Israelis tried to
do something more than what they're
doing now.
Um I think I think you're absolutely
right on that point, and it goes back to
the point of what is Israel's objective.
Is it just to weaken Iran militarily,
destroy their nuclear program, or seek a
regime change? Um you know, last couple
of topics I want to cover um with you
is um
the possibility for a peace agreement. I
know we talked about it earlier. I want
to kind of dig into it further cuz
that's what everyone's, you know, hoping
for. Um what would you put the
probability at now looking at the
narrative coming out of Israel and the
narrative coming out of Trump and the
narrative coming out of Iran which seems
to be desperate considering the messages
they're sending across through the
through the intermediaries. Cuz
initially they said, "No peace deal
unless they stop." So like now they're
like, "Peace deal if the US doesn't get
involved." Um
it does seem like desperation, I think
you'd agree.
I do agree. I do agree. I don't think
there's going to be a peace deal, but
that doesn't mean that there's not going
to be a ceasefire.
And
for for the Israelis a peace deal would
have to include some sort of diplomatic
recognition. Right? And can you imagine
any Iranian embassy in Jerusalem?
I can't.
Uh you know, the Shah's not in power
anymore. So
in terms of a formal peace deal,
not a chance. But I think that that a
a ceasefire is likely.
Where you know, let's say the Israelis
promise not to
to stop bombing, not to kill any more
members of the Iranian leadership, and
the uh Iranians will, let's say,
stop supplying Hamas and uh and
Hezbollah with
with weapons and weapons systems.
That's probably going to be it. Now the
Houthis, we haven't had a chance to talk
about the Houthis. Mhm. Um
man, we could do a whole show on the
Houthis. I've been to Yemen five times.
And every time I go, it's worse than the
previous time.
The last time I went,
I was the chief investigator on the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee, and
I went um in 20
11.
And uh
no no, this was my previous trip. 2009,
I was in a cab
going from the airport to the hotel. And
and now you can't do that. By 2011, it
was a convoy of armored cars that took
me from the airport to the to the hotel.
But anyway, I get in this cab and I said
to the cab driver,
um so how are things?
And he said, "Oh, things are bad right
now. You know, we're fighting these
Houthis, but the Saudis are helping us.
The Saudis are bombing them with
drones." And I said,
at the time, remember this is 2009, I
said, "The Saudis don't have
And then I thought, oh my god.
The Saudis don't have drones.
We have drones and they're 16 miles away
in Djibouti. And I thought, oh my god.
So I got back home and I said to John
Kerry, he was my boss,
I said, "You know, I think we're I think
we're bombing uh we're bombing Yemen.
It's an undeclared war." He's like,
"What?"
And I said, "Yeah, you know,
they're using drones against the
Houthis, but the Saudis don't have
drones.
They didn't get drones until a year
later.
And because Barack Obama was president,
John Kerry wanted to be Secretary of
State, he never raised it at the White
House.
And so we just, you know, watched it
unfold.
But we were involved
way back then in 2009 bombing the
Houthis.
The Houthis
The Houthis are gutsy people because
they have nothing to lose.
Nothing.
And so they're perfectly happy to
express solidarity by attacking
cargo ships, oil tankers, the US Navy,
whatever it is. And no matter how many
times we use million-dollar missiles
against their $10,000 drones, they don't
seem to care.
Well, now that the Israelis are just
cleaning the place up with the Iranians,
I'm wondering if the Houthis back off.
The The Iranians
The Iranians um
I'm forgive me, the Israelis
The Israelis killed a member of the
Houthi leadership.
Uh,
just a day or two after the bombing of,
uh, of Iran began.
They haven't said who that leader is,
and we haven't heard a single word about
the Houthis since this thing came out or
from the Houthis.
So, I don't know. They may have cowed
the Houthis on top of it in the
meantime.
That's a big achievement if that's the
case. So, then you have the Houthis and
Hezbollah, there's no and obviously
Hamas is decapitated as well. So, Iran's
lost all its proxies and it's lost its
military might. So, they are really
being pushed into a corner, which goes
back to the what will they do, you know,
the Putin example with the nuclear
weapon. What will Iran do when they're
in that corner?
Um,
And the So far, this is, uh, this is an
Israeli victory, no matter how you
package it, so far.
Yes.
Yeah. Like if you compare to other
military
interventions by the US in the Middle
East, nothing compares to the success
that Israel's had so far.
Agreed.
Um, and if you compare to what Russia
had in Ukraine, it's just like complete,
um,
you know, opposing outcomes. Russia
planned for one thing. I remember when I
was sitting with President Lukashenko
and he said, "Mario, Putin really didn't
plan for this long-term war, which I
think all of us knows. It's meant to be
a quick operation." Now it's into this
multi-year war. We'll see what the
outcome is.
Israel planned for something and they
got I think they got even more than they
bargained for. Like it worked with 100%
success rate.
What happens to One thing that was
heartbreaking is like I think the Iran
situation we could talk about
objectively and and blame both sides,
etc.
Uh,
and um, same for Hezbollah, you know,
Hezbollah started striking Israel
earlier. The Houthis, same thing, they
decided to ally themselves with Iran and
and Palestine or or Gaza and Hamas and
strike Israel. Israel responded. Hamas,
obviously in the beginning with October
7th,
you know, unquestionable, Israel had the
right to to respond and defend itself.
But then the war is still ongoing right
now and people talking about ethnic
cleansing, etc.
What happens to Gaza now that Iran's
completely obliterate obliterated? They
don't seem to have any allies left, so
I'm just really and it seems the Arab
world's relatively silent on this.
Is it pretty much over for Gaza?
God, I hate to say it, but yeah, I think
it is. When I was stationed in Saudi
Arabia 1991,
the Saudis asked us to deliver a message
to the Israelis and they said that they
were interested in building a port, an
airport, and
uh uh
sewer system sewage system for for Gaza
if the Israelis would allow them to do
it to help develop the Gaza economy and
to allow, you know, Gaza Palestinians to
to earn a decent living.
The Israelis said absolutely not.
Absolutely not. And since then, they
restricted, you know, the amount of
water that enters Gaza, they restricted
the the number of hours of electricity
per day.
The Gazans
finally elected Hamas because they were
so frustrated with with Israelis with
the Israeli leadership. And and then
Hamas for reasons that will never be
clear to me decided that attacking
civilians was the way to go.
Do you think Iran knew about knew about
October 7th attack and okayed it?
Oh, I think so. I think they probably
did.
What a
What a terrible mistake. Terrible
mistake.
For for the world, but especially for
Palestinians.
Especially. You know, Palestinian
the Israelis
the Israelis historically have accepted
the casualty figures that come out of
the the Gaza Ministry of Health, okay?
So, the Israelis are conceding that 90%
of the casualties in Gaza are civilians.
90%
That's unacceptable. It's a crime
against humanity.
And there's no
there's no payment that the Israelis
have to make. They're not signatories to
the ICJ or the ICC and
they don't care how many people they
kill.
So, what happens to the possibility of a
two-state solution? And again, what
happens to Gaza? Where Where do you see
Gaza in 5 years' time if there is a
Gaza?
Yeah, I think Gaza's going to be at
least as devastated as it is today
because
the truth is the Israelis continue to to
control it. They're not going to allow
the reconstruction of Gaza. They're just
not.
You know, the official policy of the
United States is
we continue to support the two-state
solution.
Maybe maybe we need to be looking at a
three-state solution.
You know, the the the West Bank, Gaza,
and Israel proper, yeah.
It's something that looks like Bosnia
with, you know, little
little patches of
land.
And like what what what you guys you
know, I I I was with in Yugoslavia not
long ago, former Yugoslavia, with uh
President um
Vucic and the President of Kosovo as
well, uh Serbia and Kosovo.
Until now, there's wounds that haven't
healed. Till now, Bosnia um I think the
I can't remember the guy's name, Dodik.
Uh
they're still, you know, Bosnia could
split into two. There's still risks of a
a a
a
a regional war a war within Bosnia.
Crazy.
A civil war there. And that's decades
after NATO's intervention. Um yes,
again, the Middle East is just such a
mess. Um
Last uh couple of questions uh
on my side, John, I appreciate your time
is uh
where do you see this in, let's say, 12
months' time considering where things
are are at right now? And you can offer
different scenarios.
Oh, I think that uh
I think we're going to enter into uh
some sort of
ceasefire agreement, peace agreement
probably in the coming weeks
between the Israelis and the Iranians,
but I don't see any real changes in
Gaza.
There's there's no one to help the
Gazans anymore,
right? The Syrians are gone, Hezbollah's
decapitated, the Iranians are in chaos,
the Houthis have just thrown up their
their hands. I think that on a
humanitarian level, it's going to
actually be worse for Palestinians in 12
months' time.
And for the region, do you think it
could lead to more peace now that that
power struggle between
Iran and their allies and their proxies
versus Saudi and their proxies, allies,
or Western allies, that's pretty much
come to an end. Has Israel potentially
done a favor for the region excluding
Palestine?
How how crazy is that, right? But yeah,
it seems that way.
It it seems that way. As soon as Assad
ran to ran to Moscow, the Saudis
reestablished diplomatic relations with
Damascus. That was huge. And as I said,
whatever the Saudis do, the Bahrainis
do. And the the Emiratis are joined at
the hip with the Saudis. So now there's
this new age of diplomatic relations,
they're going to help to rebuild Syria,
everything's going to be fine, but they
have to smash Hezbollah.
Right?
I think that's what's going to end up
happening.
And uh
And then once that happens, I
I can't even believe I'm going to say
the words, but I think
I think the Saudis are going to finally
establish diplomatic relations with
Israel.
It's a business decision.
And what happens so so one more
question, I know I said this is it, but
there's a lot of countries neighboring
Israel that are really worried right now
that Israel's ambitions are beyond
Gaza and Palestinian territory. You
know, they're they're still in Syria,
they're still in Lebanon. Could that
lead to the acquisition of more
territory? You know, when they you
declare war on another country, you
know, you look at most wars, World Wars,
the winner ends up taking up more land.
That's like kind of the price that you
get. Could
the cost be that Israel
keeps certain land in in Syria and like
the Golan Heights in Syria and and in
Lebanon?
Number one and number two, do you see
peace between those countries and
Israel? Is there a possibility that
Lebanon and Syria do prosper moving
forward and does Israel want them to
prosper? Then again, this is a point
that's heavily debated right now.
I don't think Israel wants them to
prosper because when there's internal
chaos, that helps to keep the Israelis
safe. When there's internal political
chaos.
You know, the Israelis don't want them
to be unified because then they could
turn their attention to Israel. Number
one. Number two, I think the Israelis
well, the Israelis already have annexed
the Golan Heights. So, Golan is not
going to return to Syria. Right now, the
the Israelis have taken another 20 km or
so beyond Golan.
That's unacceptable.
And I think probably the Israelis are
going to have to pull back out and give
it back. But I wouldn't be surprised if
there's some sort of informal agreement
between Jolani and Syria, the new the
new leader of Syria and the Israelis,
even if it's sort of an under the table
deal negotiated with the Americans,
that the Israelis stay on their side of
the line and the Syrians will stay on
their side of the line.
And for Lebanon?
You know, poor Lebanon.
Such a nice country and such a terrible
situation. I I don't I don't see any
good news for Lebanon.
I really don't.
Heartbreaking.
John Kiriakou, really appreciate the
time spent in credible discussion. Your
expertise on the on the region has been
has been refreshing. So, I appreciate
your time, sir.
Thanks so much for the invitation. It's
a real pleasure to meet you.